My father-in-law is a farmer. This is
one of his peach trees. And he says that
when you're pruning a peach tree, you
want gaps big enough in the peach tree
that you can throw a chicken through
them. And I don't know if that's just
him or that's a thing that people say a
lot. But it makes me think about
business. And the profit margin you're
looking for when you're looking at a
accounting firm usually cuz that's
primarily what I deal with. But when
you're looking Oh gosh, that might have
been a chicken. Oh, that's probably why.
Maybe they used to have chickens.
Anyways, when you're looking at a firm
and you're looking at buying it, a lot
of times people are throwing around two
basic accounts of what the general
profit is. One is SDE, sellers
discretionary earnings, and one is
IBIDA. IBIDA is often used in bigger
companies. Sellers discretionary
earnings is more commonly used in a
situation where you have like one owner
operator and another owner operator is
coming to the equation um to replace the
initial one. So that owner operator in
that context just means somebody who
owns the business is also doing the work
and running it dayto-day. So SDE
seller's discretionary earnings is a
perfect thing to be considered when
you're stepping into the shoes of the
seller. So if I'm one buyer and buying a
100% owned company, I am going to
replace the seller with myself. I can
say, well, what did that guy bring home
or girl? Right? Like would they pay
themselves? What's their self-employment
IRA look like? Do they run their vehicle
through the company? you know, do they
pay their son and then I can, you know,
put know that I'll get that money back.
You know, there's a million different
ways that people wind up actually
compensating themselves when they're
running a company. And all of those I
step into the shoes of if I'm the
subsequent owner operator. So, solar
discretionary earnings makes a ton of
sense. IBIDA is more of a function that
you would use if you're not going to
operate the company. So if you have to
take that owner operator who was doing
all those things and replace them with
just somebody who costs $150,000 a year,
then you know that what's left is the
IBIDA. It can be really hard. That
sounds so simple, right? You just
replace the owner operator with somebody
who costs $150,000 a year. That is super
challenging in practice because people
don't really run businesses like an
owner unless they are an owner. So
having somebody who can replace an owner
usually takes more than one person in my
experience. Uh if you're replacing one
owner operator with the other, seller
discretionary earnings makes sense. If
you're buying a business, you've already
got a job and you're running it fully as
a investment vehicle. You're going to be
managing it remotely while everybody
else does the work. That's more of an
EVA consideration. Where it gets tricky
is where you have three owner operators
and one person buying it. So you kind of
want to back out. Usually for SDE
analysis, you're trying to normalize for
one owner operator. So you would in that
instance you would back out the salary
for one of the three partners and kind
of do a hybrid adjusted IBIDA for that.
That's how those are typically used in
my world to evaluate the profit of a
company and it's mostly perspective.
It's mostly saying how do I figure out
how much money I'm going to make as the
owner of this company. And ultimately
that's usually what matters to the
buyer. So I'm Sarah Sharp. If you found
this valuable please engage with the
content. Go check out dealacademy.org.
forward.